Guide to the Carolyn Horton and Associates Records
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Carolyn Horton and Associates Records
1919-1988.
Carolyn Horton and Associates.
16.5 linear ft (ca. 21,000 items in 41 boxes & 2 card file boxes).
Columbia University, Rare Book and Manuscript Library, Butler Library, New York, NY 10027.
4079522
History
Bookbinding and restoration; Document restoration including manuscripts, maps and works of art on paper.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, subject files, business, personnel, biographical files and financial records. The correspondence files deal with clients: individuals, libraries, museums and book dealers. The chronological files are letters with individual clients, while the alphabetical clients files contain folders for institutional clients, and also include topical subject headings such as "Libraries", "Museums", and headings for specific books and works of art. The subject files contain manuscripts, notes for seminars and lectures given by Carolyn Horton on the preservation of books and paper documents and include files on floods, particularly the 1966 flood in Florence, Italy, wet books, form letters, rubbings of books and sample paper. The business records consist of detailed worksheets arranged by client, describing condition of items bound or restored and the type of work done on these items; and complete financial records, i.e., bills, receipts, accounts and personnel records, including payroll, taxes, health insurance and other benefits, which document the operations of a bindery and paper restoration firm. The card file boxes contain details of work done arranged by artist name and by genre, i.e., music, portraits, newspapers, vellum, etc. The biographical files consist of correspondence, notebooks and newspaper clippings relating to Horton's career including her discovery that freezing wet books prevents their molding.
Arrangement
Series 1. Box 1-9: correspondence files; Box 10-11: subject files (conservation & restoration topics); Box 12-21: business records; Box 22-28: financial records; Box 29-31: personnel records; Card file box 1-2: artist & genre files.
Series 2. Box 32: correspondence files; financial records; biographical files A-B; Box 33: biographical files C-P; Boxes 34-37: subject files A-Y; Box 38: subject files--lectures; Box 39: business files.
Subjects
Bookbinding--United States--20th century.; Manuscripts--Conservation and restoration.; Art--Conservation and restoration.; Financial records.; Lectures.; Personnel records.; Rubbings.; Bookbinders--United States--20th century; Document restorers.
Access Restrictions
This collection is located off-site. You will need to request this material at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
Acquisition
07/27/87 records Horton, Carolyn Gift
05/16/90 M-90-05-16 Correspondence, financial records, subject files, lectures, business records and biographical meterial. 4 linear ft (ca. 3,000 items in 8 boxes) Horton, Carolyn Gift, 1990
Gift of Carolyn Horton, 1987, 1989, & 1990.
- Series I
  - Correspondence Files
    - Chronological
      - 1932-1961 (Box 1)
      - 1962-1979 (Box 2)
      - 1980-1987 (Box 3)
    - Clients
      - A-Coo (Box 4)
      - Cor-F (Box 5)
      - G-L (Box 6)
      - M-National Agricultural Library (NAL) (Box 7)
      - National Library of Medicine (NLM)-S (Box 8)
      - Universities (Box 9)
  - Subject Files
    - Conservation paper, Form letters, Floods, Rubbings of books, Sample paper, Seminars & lectures, Wet books, 1931-1980 (Box 10)
    - Florence Flood, 1966-1970 (Box 11)
  - Business Records
    - Client Sheet Bindery
      - A-M, 1966-1984 (Box 12)
      - N-Z, 1966-1984 (Box 13)
      - Corning, National Agricultural Library (NAL), Northwestern University Dental School, New York Public Library 1973-1982 (Box 14)
      - A-G, 1972-1984 (Box 15)
      - H-Z, 1971-1984 (Box 16)
    - Fine Hand Binding (restoration of books worksheets)
      - A-D, 1973-1982 (Box 17)
      - E-L, 1973-1982 (Box 18)
      - L-R, 1974-1979 (Box 19)
      - S-Z, 1973-1982 (Box 20)
    - Insurance Policies, 1973-1982 (Box 21)
  - Financial Records
    - Bills, Receipts, and Accounts
      - A-F, 1968-1980 (Box 22)
      - G-R, 1974-1979 (Box 23)
      - S-Z, 1976-1983 (Box 24)
    - Business bills, receipts, 1972-1984 (Box 25)
    - Clients' bills, 1955-1966 (Box 26)
    - Payroll journal, payroll books, 1976-1983 (Box 27)
    - Sales slips, sales journal, A - Z, 1981-1984 (Box 28)
  - Personnel Records
    - Benefits and Insurance, 1971-1984 (Box 29)
    - Employees and applicants, 1976- 1983 (Box 30)
    - Time Sheets, 1974- 1979 (Box 31)
  - Card File Boxes
    - Artists
      - A-S, 1971-1984 (Box Card File Box 1)
      - T-Z, 1971-1984 (Box Card File Box 2)
    - Untreated genre file (i.e. autographs, books, diaries, duckstamps, maps, photographs, etc.) (Box Card File Box 2)
- Series II
  - Correspondence Files, 1971-1986 (Box 32)
  - Financial Records, 1940-1978 (Box 32)
  - Biographical Files
    - A-B, 1952-1984 (Box 32)
    - C-P, 1933-1984 (Box 33)
  - Subject Files
    - A, 1935-1983 (Box 34)
    - B, 1936-1979 (Box 35)
    - C-Mi, 1965-1987 (Box 36)
    - Mo-Y, 1936-1981 (Box 37)
    - Lectures, 1961-1979 (Box 38)
  - Business Files-- Schedules, insurance forms, contracts, etc., 1919-1988 (Box 39)